Java provides a number of classes and methods that allow you to read and write files. Of course, the most common types of files are disk files. In Java, all files are byte-oriented, and Java provides methods to read and write bytes from and to a file. Thus, reading and writing files using byte streams is very common. However, Java allows you to wrap a byte-oriented file stream within a character-based object, which is shown later in this chapter.